<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title><![CDATA[Shape Shed]]></title><link href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/shapeshed" rel="self"></link><link href="http://shapeshed.com"></link><updated>2015-09-21T17:33:55.082Z</updated><id><![CDATA[http://shapeshed.com/]]></id><author><name><![CDATA[George Ornbo]]></name></author><generator uri="https://github.com/shapeshed/flim">Flim</generator><entry><title type="html"><![CDATA[CS50 Section 2015]]></title><link href="http://shapeshed.com/cs50_2015"></link><updated>2015-09-21T04:00:00.000Z</updated><id>http://shapeshed.com/cs50_2015</id><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Section Week 2</h3>
<p>Pre-section survey link: <a href="https://docs.google.com/a/college.harvard.edu/forms/d/1AXGbJYdmkrwZT6G6cBnaZFsrh9heGLSx27lC5z4bd7k/viewform?usp=send_form" title="Pre-section survey.">here</a></p>
<p>Slides: <a href="/assets/cs50/week2.pptx">PPTX</a> <a href="/assets/cs50/week2.pdf">PDF</a></p>
<p>Code (available after section): </p>
<p>Post-section survey: <a href="https://docs.google.com/a/college.harvard.edu/forms/d/1_AQxk-Ai0L_Ofo28U50HhyfsYQQaWlSPBWnkfoD_LAM/viewform?usp=send_form">here</a></p>
]]></content></entry><entry><title type="html"><![CDATA[A New Graph/FSM Drawer Is Born]]></title><link href="http://shapeshed.com/undirected_graphs"></link><updated>2015-09-10T04:00:00.000Z</updated><id>http://shapeshed.com/undirected_graphs</id><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Making My Own Life Easier, and Hopefully Yours Too</h2>
<p>Blogging about my summer didn&#39;t really go anywhere, but I have something to post now.</p>
<p>I&#39;m taking two courses this fall at Harvard related directly to graph theory: <a href="http://lewis.seas.harvard.edu/pages/computer-science-121-and-csci-e-121-introduction-theory-computation">CS 121, Theory of Computation</a>, and <a href="http://networksatharvard.com">CS 134, Networks</a>. I anticipate having to draw lots of graphs on problem sets this semester.</p>
<p>When I&#39;ve had to draw graphs (or finite state machines, which are graphs in their own right) for classes in the past, I discovered <a href="http://madebyevan.com/fsm">an FSM utility</a>. If you&#39;ve ever tried to use the tikzpicture package in LaTeX, you know that it isn&#39;t particularly quick or easy: that site made the process quick by generating LaTeX from an HTML canvas, where you can draw an FSM.</p>
<p>That was fine until this fall, when I need to be able to draw undirected graphs. After realizing that delete the arrows from the generated LaTeX was really tedious, I decided to fork the generator and make it more general.</p>
<p>So I did! You can find it at greensam.github.io/fsm. Hope it&#39;s useful to you. </p>
]]></content></entry><entry><title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to samuelgreen.org]]></title><link href="http://shapeshed.com/welcome_to_samuelgreen.org"></link><updated>2015-06-21T04:00:00.000Z</updated><id>http://shapeshed.com/welcome_to_samuelgreen.org</id><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Back from the Dead</h2>
<p>I have a long history of blogging. Sadly, my history of not blogging is just as distinguished: each of my past attempts has ended a cleverly title chronicle of my life slowly drifting into oblivion. Here we are again.</p>
<p>As is periodically my custom, I realized earlier this weekend that it&#39;s rather shameful as a developer to have a poor web presence of my own. I was therefore inspired to once again revamp my personal website -- after all, I have this fancy URL, so I may as well use it. I wanted to get back to blogging, as well, and I realized that my rails site really wasn&#39;t going to let me do that simply.</p>
<p>I figured, why not take this moment to investigate something more light weight. I stumbled upon flim and shapeshed.com from @shapeshed, and here we are. Also a chance to practice my markdown. </p>
<p>I&#39;m not sure where I want this blog to go, but I know already that writing again will bring a much needed dose of catharsis. I&#39;m working my first job in industry as a developer right now, so there might be some posts about that, but I&#39;ve also found in college that my expository writing skills (i.e. writing down my godforsaken opinions) have dulled a bit as I&#39;ve dedicated more energy to the quantitive arts. So there&#39;ll be some of that too. </p>
<p>I hope you&#39;ll stick around for the ride. </p>
]]></content></entry></feed>